A Guide to the Tracy W. McGregor Autograph Collection, ca. 1599-1947
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- SERIES III: SLIPCASE COLLECTIONS
  - Letters of James Monroe to Stephen Pleasonton 1811-1831, 33 ALS & TLS, in blue slipcase (Othertype 49)
    Discusses the purchase of horses from Isaac McCuddy (1811 Sep 3); transport of prisoners (1814 Mar 29; Apr 16); written to Dr. Jones of Northumberland County to authorize sending an agent to the [West Indies?] to look after the slaves from that quarter and the country between the Northern Neck and Norfolk (1815 May 18); his financial affairs suffered from his absence on duty to his country, his health improving, and various business in the State Department (1815 May through Sep); his claim to the comptroller for additional compensation for his former mission to France and other missions which caused him to have to borrow money (1816 Nov 21; 1826 Jan 12, 23, 25, Feb 4; Apr 10); the death of his grandchild, the daughter of Mrs. Gouverneur and a request for all proper assistance to several office seekers (1821 Sep 15); sends letters to Pleasonton to forward to his friends in France (1827 Mar 28; 1828 Apr 7); the meeting of the Board of Visitors at the University of Virginia (1829 Jul 26); the plan for an executive government at the University of Virginia and his financial difficulties (1830 May 2; 1831 Apr); including a typed letter, 1911 Nov 4, from Roswell Randall Hoes concerning Monroe family genealogy. # 495
  - Account book of George Weedon 1777-1793, AMs, 120p., in a blue slipcase (Othertype 50)
    Including accounts of George Weedon with Fontaine Maury, James Monroe, William Mercer, Timothy Green, John Minor, the Fredericksburg Academy, the estate of Hugh Mercer, of which Weedon was executor, and soldiers stationed at the Sentry Box. Account entries are primarily for cash, but also include entries for the delivery of wood, personal and household expenses, slave hires, legal services, lottery prizes, sundries and building supplies. # 2525
  - Peter Force scrapbook about James Madison 1812-1857, Bound scrapbook, 95p., in tan slipcase (Othertype 51)
    Chiefly clippings, obituary notices and eulogies. There are also clippings about incidents in Madison's life and administration, particularly during the War of 1812, as well as tipped in prospectuses for a biography and his papers. There are copies of Madison speeches and letters, and letters from Dolley Payne Todd Madison and J.C. Payne. # 9911
  - Correspondence of Sir Andrew Snape Hamond (1738-1828)and Hans Stanley, governor of the Isle of Wight, including one letter from Hans Sloane to Hamond 1766, 1771-1778, 23 ALS (Othertype 52)
    Discusses a naval appointment, a land settlement scheme on the Ohio opposed by Lord Hillsborough, the Gasp饠affair, Bunker Hill, naval operations in Virginia and on the Delaware (Lord Dunmore's retreat), the Staten Island Peace Conference, Saratoga, General Burgoyne, the burning of New York, Hessians, consequences of the American-French alliance, British foreign and economic affairs, and the guardianship of Felix Viret. # 4390
  - Memoirs of A.S. Hamond entitled "Heads of the Life of Sir Andrew Snape Hamond Bart. written merely for the Private Information of his own Family; as the Narrative will shew; being of little Interest to the world at large" ca. 1815, 2 AMs, 88 & 86 p., in a blue slipcase (Othertype 53)
    Consists of two volumes with marbled paper wrappers, labeled "First" and "Second," in A.S. Hamond's autograph, with occasional comments added by G.E. Hamond, and covering Hamond's career as an active sea officer from 1769 until 1794, when he went to the Navy Board after an illness; glued into the front of book two is an unsigned, hand-drawn map, in color, of the area from Philadelphia westward, illustrating the Brandywine campaign. # 680
  - Account of Andrew Snape Hamond's part in the American Revolution, 1775-1777 1783-1785, 3 AMs, 56, 73, & 44p., in three volumes with marbled paper wrappers, in the hand of Hamond, in a blue slipcase (Othertype 54)
    Beginning with his appointment to The Roebuck, her departure from England in September 1775, his first stay at Halifax, his share in the blockade of the Jersey Coast; Delaware Bay and Chesapeake Bay; his covering of the landing of Sir William Howe's troops for the Battle of Long Island; and expedition to Antigua and the Leeward Islands; and ends with the capture and occupation of Philadelphia in 1777. Includes many observations and anecdotes on the conduct of the Revolution, including the "peace offensive" by Lord Howe and Sir William Howe to George Washington, the difficulties of the British with the defenses of Philadelphia, and the barriers the Americans placed in the Delaware River invented by Dr. Franklin. # 680
  - Logbook, in a vellum bound volume, entitled "An Account of the Progress & Proceedings of His Majesty's Frigate Arethusa of 32 Guns between the 17 June 1771 and the 28 November 1773 during the time she was commanded by Captain A.S. Hamond kept by himself, 165 pages; consisting of descriptions of the ports visited by Hamond, including Norfolk, Boston, New York, Philadelphia, Williamsburg, Newport, Providence, Halifax, St. Johns, etc. with day to day information about weather, course, changes of sail and ship routines; and including in the same volume, "A Journal of the Roebucks Second Voyage to North America" [May through October 1779] 13 pages of narrative. 1771-1773, 1779, AMs, in a blue slipcase (Othertype 55)
    # 680
  - A single vellum bound volume combination Letter Book and Order Book belonging to A.S. Hamond ca. 1771-1777, AMs, in a blue slipcase (Othertype 56)
    In several distinct sections, including: Letters sent and received, December 28, 1771- December 29, 1777, while he was on the Barfleur, Arethusa, and the Roebuck, 50 pages; and Orders issued and received, 1772-1777, while commanding the Arethusa, and the Roebuck, including important data on the methods of signaling in the British Navy, as adapted to service during the American Revolution, a copy of the resolution of the Pennsylvania Council of Safety, December 21, 1776, pages 105-110. # 680
  - Letter Book kept by A.S. Hamond, in a single vellum bound volume, while in command of the Roebuck, March 3, 1776- December 9, 1777, 72 pages, including a copy of a letter from Lord Howe to Hamond, April 24, 1777 1776-1777, AMs, in a blue slipcase (Othertype 57)
    #680
  - Letter Book and Order Book kept by A.S. Hamond, in command of the Roebuck, 38 pages and 48 pages; and in the same volume, the Letter Book and Order Book, 1799, kept by Captain Graham Eden Hamond, who apparently used an old record book of his father to record part of his own involvement in the British Navy during the Napoleonic Wars, in command of the Champion1778-1780, 1799, AMs, in a blue slipcase (Othertype 58)
  - Letter Book kept by A.S. Hamond, August 2, 1781-January 21, 1783 1781-1783, AMs, 176 pages, in a calf bound folio, in a blue slipcase (Othertype 59)
  - Letter Book kept by A.S. Hamond, August 3, 1781-October 8, 1782 1781-1782, AMs, 36 pages, in vellum bound folio, in a blue slipcase (Othertype 60)
    Correspondents similar to those in slipcase 59, apparently Hamond started two letter books simultaneously, one for letters to superiors, and one to subordinates, but his secretary used them indiscriminately. #680
  - Order Book of Captain A.S. Hamond, August 1, 1781-January 5, 1783 1781-1783, AMs, 204 pages, with an index, 24 pages, in a calf bound folio, in a blue slipcase (Othertype 61)
    Concerning routine matters when Hamond was in command at Halifax. #680
  - A Chronological list of the captains of his majesty's royal navy, with dates of their first commissions, promotions, and other occurrences, commencing the 21st June, 1673, in the reign of King Charles II and brought down to the year 1783(London, 1784). 1784, Print, 95 pages, with additional manuscript notes and marginalia by [Graham Eden] Hamond, in a blue slipcase (Othertype 62)
  - Letter Book kept by Admiral Graham Eden Hamond, while commanding the Plantagenet and the Lively1803-1806, AMs, in vellum covers, in a blue slipcase (Othertype 63)
    Concerning Hamond's voyages in Cawesand Bay, Woolwich, Gravesend, Spithead, Portsmouth, Cartagena, Lagos River, Cadiz, Tagus, Lisbon, Gibralter, Malta, Valetta Harbor, Naples, and Messina. #4609
  - Courts martial, Port Book, Correspondence and Orders, kept by Admiral Graham Eden Hamond, in vellum covers, including "Remarks on Courts Martial", 104 numbered pages, with five page index preceding; Incomplete Table of Arrivals and Sailings at Malta; Letters sent while commanding the Lively, May 30, 1805- May 7, 1806; and Orders issued June 27, 1805-April 3, 1806, while commanding the Lively1805-1806, AMs, in a blue slipcase (Othertype 64)
    #4609
  - Order Book kept by Admiral Graham Eden Hamond, while commanding the Victorious, the Rivoli, the Wellesley, and the Spartiate, including a detailed report, May 28, 1808, on the naval uniform worn at all ranks, and details concerning cruises off the coasts of Portugal and Spain, the Channel, the Mediterranean Sea, and a trip to Rio de Janeiro in 1825 1808-09, 1813-14, 1824-25, In a blue slipcase (Othertype 65)
  - Orders and Regulations written by Admiral Graham Eden Hamond, "Orders and regulations to be observed by the officers and Ships Company of His Majesty's Ship Under My Command, In Addition to those contained in the General printed Instructions, pages 1-15; Orders concerning the "exercise for great guns" based upon the orders of the Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty of 1 August 1817, pages 15-20 [ca. 1828], In a blue slipcase (Othertype 66)
  - "A Narrative of the Professional Service of G.E. Hamond," 100 pages (1812); and "Statement of His Service,"(1815); and two letters, 1778 & 1793 1778-1815, AMs & 2 ALS, in a blue slipcase (Othertype 67)
    Eden begins with his service in 1785 as a Captain's servant and continues through the Napoleonic Wars. It contains accounts of all ships on which he sailed, admirals under whom he served, including Hyde Parker and Horatio Nelson, actions in which he was engaged and enemy ships captured. He describes the battle of Copenhagen, sieges of Malta and Flushing and action at Naples. There are personal notes on health and travels, and observations on the British custom of requiring other ships to salute her colors. With the memoirs are a letter granting permission to publish, 1823; a letter, 1793, as a midshipman, relating an encounter with the French fleet with a sketch of the ships' positions; and a letter, 1778, from Charles Henri, Comte d'Estaing, to Louis Antoine de Bougainville on naval matters. #680-b
  - "Dream of John Ball" by William Morris 1884, AMsS, 100p., in vellum binding (Othertype 68)
    #38-734
  - "High and Low Life in Italy," by Walter Savage Landor, fictitious correspondence originally published in the Monthly Repository between August 1837 and April 1838 1837-1838, AMs, 89p., in red slipcase (Othertype 69)
    #38-738
  - Bibliography of the Statute Law of the Southern States by Theodore Lee Cole (1852-1932), a portion of the manuscript covering Georgia and Arkansas [1897?], AMsS, 46p., in brown slipcase (Othertype 70)
    #9277
  - Notebook of a Scottish horticulturist [Fletcher?] of Whitton, near Jedburgh 1723-1748, AMs, 58p., in a green slipcase (Othertype 71)
    Recording dates of sowing, germination, blossoming and places of origin of plants in his garden, and occasionally the agent from whom they were obtained. He checked his own varieties against a list of rare species, noted seeds that could be imported from the North American colonies, especially Virginia, North Carolina, and Maryland, and from Spain and Aleppo, Syria. #9897
  - Manuscript Crop Manual "On the Produce of the Colonies" by Mr. [John?] Rutherford 1760, AMs, in a green slipcase (Othertype 72)
    He discusses corn, tobacco, wheat, rice, indigo, and silk. #9897
  - Natural History manuscripts and letters kept by Cromwell Mortimer, Secretary of the Royal Society 1747-1748, AMs, all docketed by Cromwell Mortimer, in a blue slipcase (Othertype 73)
    Probably for publication in their papers, including an extract of an article by Dr. James Mounsey, "An Account of a Woman Who Harbored a [the bones of a] Foetus thirteen years in her body" at Riga, Russia, presented by Henry Baker; a letter from Henry Baker (1698-1774) to the President of the Royal Society, Martin Folkes, concerning the previous article about the Russian woman; "Several Essays towards discovering the laws of electricity" by John Ellicott (1706?-1772); partial letter from Abbe Jean Antoine Nollet (1700-1770) concerning electricity; manuscript by Sir William Watson (1715-1787) concerning his electrical experiments and mentioning experiments conducted by "an ingenious gentleman ... in Pennsylvania" [Ben Franklin]; "Account of the Giant's Causeway in Ireland, in a letter to the President from the Rev. Richard Pococke, Archdeacon of Dublin"; a letter and diagram of a metal thermometer by Maurice Johnson; abstract of a letter from the Jesuit missionary Father Bonaventure Suares about astronomical observations, a printed page on lunar eclipses observed in Paraguay, and notes on solar eclipses, 1706-1730; a manuscript concerning the motion of projectiles near the earth's surface by Thomas Simpson (1710-1761); an abstract of a letter from William Anderson to Henry Baker concerning the hearing of fish; and a copy of an inscription at Stanhope upon a Roman altar [by the Rev. Mr. Keene?]. #4530-a
  - Virginia Gazette Daybooks (2 volumes), kept in Williamsburg, Virginia, containing accounts for subscriptions, advertisements, books (including almanacs, Bibles, and law books) 1750-1752, 1764-1766, Binding, stationery, blanks, and forms, especially legal forms and other forms for court use (Othertype 74-75)
    #467
  - Watercolor Sketches by Paul Braddon, "Haunts of Charles Lamb," including the birthplace of Lamb at Temple, London; his residence at Islington; the bell at Edmonton; Blakesware House; farm at Mackery End; his last home at Edmonton; "Ye King & Tinker Inn" at Enfield; Widford Church; the cottage at Enfield; "The Bell Inn" at Widford; Edmonton Church where Charles Lamb is buried; and Charles Lamb's house on Little Queen street n.d., Watercolors (Othertype 76)
    #10547-df
  - Scrapbook containing about 250 eighteenth and nineteenth century engravings and related correspondence ca. 1870 (Othertype 77)
    Presumed to be part of the McGregor-Mather Collection. #38-632-c
- SERIES IV. BOUND MCGREGOR MEDIEVAL MANUSCRIPTS
  - Bible 13th century (Othertype N)
    Vellum, 603 ff., 16 x 11 cm. Written in France, diapered text in a fine hand, in Latin, 47 lines per column. Numerous historiated and illuminated initials, text occasionally rubricated, red and blue pen decoration throughout. Bound in old brown velvet, two silver clasps, gilt demi-lion rampant with devise ( nobilis ira) on upper cover, gauffered edges. Provenance notes and bookplates inside endpapers. #38-728
  - Horae, Book of Hours 15th century (Othertype O)
    Written in France, vellum, 120 ff., 19 x 14 cm. The calendar is written in French and Latin; the remainder is in Latin. The final leaf carries a prayer written in a contemporary cursive Latin hand. 19 large miniatures, richly decorated and liberally gilt; numerous floriated borders and illuminated initials. Bound in the 19th century in brown Levant morocco, elaborately blind-tooled, gilt edges; brown morocco slipcase. Provenance note (1683) on recto of first leaf. #38-728
  - Horae, Book of Hours, Rheims use. ca. 1490 (Othertype P)
    Vellum, 85 ff., 19 x 14 cm., written in northern France. The calendar is written in French; the remainder is in Latin with the exception of leaves 1-2, 50v, 51-53, 83-85, which are written in French by a different hand. Mounted ecclesiastical ex libris, with 6 large miniatures, possibly by Jean or Pierre Herlin, and 8 large illuminated initials, all with richly floriated borders; many smaller illuminated initials; text occasionally rubricated. Bound in 16th century French morocco, elaborate gilt covers and edges, two clasps missing. Provenance notes inside upper cover. #38-728